[Music]
so welcome to today's solution raising
we are discussing
religion more the community aspect of
religion that was also possible i didn't
put the video up beforehand was it was
hard to kind of
name it in a way that started the
conversation
around community and anyway we knew what
we were talking about the three of us
came up the last week so we can
we can get more into it so anyone wants
to start
sharing what community what religion
and or church has looked like in their
life
the good the bad the ugly in society
i've i've found i don't know if any of
you remember there was a
interview one of the first ones i saw of
jordan's possibly the first one i saw of
jordan's called paradox of the times
that he did on rebel wisdom and towards
the end of that
he talked about religion
and sort of broke it down his various
pieces and so basically his point was
um that religion as we currently use the
word is sort of a giant basket which
contains a whole bunch of stuff
um you know what is the nature of god
what's right what's moral how to where
did the world come from where did we
come from what's our purpose blah blah
blah blah blah all of this stuff
is dumped into the one basket of
religion and
um he sort of split these things apart
into spirituality and mysticism and
religion and science right and that each
of these has a role to play in in what
we come to understand religion so
the religion as a community activity
which is what you want to focus on in
this i think right is is what he used
the word religion
for where religion is where people come
together
and celebrate worship honor
whatever something that is bigger than
all of them
but of which they are also all apart
right and so it it it's
social glue is i'm not sure if that was
jordan's term or somebody else but i
really like that term of social blue
where
you come together and you sing songs and
you dance and you build a fire
um and you write stories and you you
know laugh and cry and whatever you know
that
these so a funeral would be a religious
whether whether it's
you know in a church yard or not whether
it's in a synagogue or not irrelevant
right
a a a funeral is a perfect example of a
religious
gathering where people are coming
together to honor the life of someone
and to um send them well to their death
kind of thing right it's something
that's bigger than them they're all part
of it but it's bigger than any of them
and so yeah that that i i thought it
would be a good place to start with
just sort of framing the context of what
really community religion is kind of
about because i really like that i've
found those framings be really really
really useful
in terms of thinking about this stuff so
jared the topic today is religion
especially in context of community
all right daniel you want to share yeah
i can go next
um yeah agree with a lot of what you
said eric
um i'm gonna just try to follow as best
i can the format of just starting with
describing
the problem and one thing that i've
noticed
is my my understanding of religion
is and this is as opposed to
spirituality
uh religion means something that you do
regularly
that's like the root word relegare
is is latin it's it's it means to bind
it's something that you do
regularly um you know you can you can
religiously
wash your car once a month if you do it
once a month and so
this is where we get people gathering um
you know usually on sundays sometimes on
fridays sometimes on saturdays but
if i'm gathering you know we're almost
doing this
religiously every wednesday and there's
something good about that regularity
um and uh
it's really sad to me um
because
we get really confused
is is what i noticed because there are
good things
in some of these religions and there's
bad things
and um i guess what i notice
is there's people that
are that get hurt by religious
communities
and or you know
confused by part of the things that
are wrong or incorrect like from a
scientific perspective or something
um and so i guess is a little bit like a
jordan peterson type of thing that we
don't need to throw the whole thing
out um and
you know what i think is missing is
focusing
on the good parts about it what are the
parts that focus on
love and bringing people together
and grace and forgiveness
um there are so many good aspects
to religious practices
including the um the regular coming
together
that is community building
and i guess i
throwing out religion entirely
loses some of the good things i want to
be able to tease out
the good parts about it
without just going into total
chaos um i guess that's that's most of
what i have to say
um there there are so many good parts
to it and it's it's like what we focus
on
um seems to matter you know i could talk
for a long time about the parts of
religion i
i don't like and i disagree with um but
there's a whole other part of the
conversation
uh that i'd like to have more yeah i'm
looking forward to hearing what your
your beautiful vision
of the future is um my for this part
what is i grew up in an evangelical
christian home
and religion was a very foundational
part of that
i mean everything was run through what
is the
what does our church leaders think what
does the bible say
and what is is this right within that um
and so now that i'm older i'm in no way
looking to recreate that i don't want
there to be something else that's
deciding how i live my life
god or anything but there are parts that
i absolutely miss
there are i miss singing together i miss
intergenerational community that you get
to show you get to see people from you
know newborn babies up through
the elderly and they're all part of the
same community that doesn't happen many
places
and um that that community that sense of
coming together
every sunday of eating together of
sharing in that and sharing in each
other's lives
of knowing that there's people who have
your back if i remember when we were
we had harder christmas times and easier
christmas times and the church would you
know help with with gifts and food
on the gears when we didn't have a lot
and there is
a safety net that exists there that has
now been taken over by the government
organizations for better or worse and i
think we can bring back some of that
i had um two experiences i want to share
briefly one of which is when i was
cooking with community one of the people
who's very christian
and very uh is like a minister in his
church
i was talking about what my church would
look like
and i mentioned that what i would love
is to be singing out in nature with
people
and he was like oh yeah my friend does
that
i have yet to get that friend's number
but i'm like how awesome that the thing
that i'm like nobody else would want to
do this was exactly what what he offered
and then i had
a um a roommate who happened to be
muslim and she was living away from her
her teenage kids and she was going
through ramadan and it was
ramadan is a very social time in a very
hard time
you don't drink water you don't do all
of this stuff from sun up to sun down
and during
solstice in canada that's a long time
and she was looking for a um
a mosque and she that was like somewhat
in alignment with her values and it was
next to impossible for her to find one
even though there's tons of mosques in
the lower mainland and to be able to
have that
that was where the spark of um
a tool to be able to help with those
things to be able to help find your
your church for you that is in your
religion
and a connection i know my mom's had the
same problem with christianity like
this church is too loud and this one
does too much for this and not enough
for this to be able to find that
that sweet spot for you so jared what
would you like to share a dream
sure uh yeah i echo a lot of your
sentiment
who was raised in an evangelical
christian uh household
uh also is is my how's my zoom call is
is it choppy or am i good because i've
been having fun
[Music]
good okay um so
i i definitely i could go on all day on
in terms of like what i would want to
see the religion that's not a religion
look like right but i feel like everyone
kind of has
um a good sense of what that would be
which is
stripping dogma from religion
and then see what's left and kind of see
the
um the
i mean the whole idea behind it is
bringing community together to support
each other
and have a
system where you have people
intergenerationally
intergenerationally that support each
other and
um to me
that seems like it seems like a really
hard thing to do
[Music]
on a massive scale without
some greater thing
that this this big either fear or this
big existential answer
where it's like what happens when i die
oh okay
like i will follow this book
and that way i'll go to heaven when i
die okay
that's why i'm going to do something
right like it's
it's a massive motivator for for
actually taking action
so what other big motivators can there
be
to have people join a large
community that isn't necessarily
telling people the way the world is um
and to me i don't know it it seems
it seems as if um i know andrew yang has
a really cool idea about modern time
banking
where uh he you he wants to create an
app
that allows the tracking of
like volunteering within your community
and
people can actually get incentivized to
come together and work together so
maybe there's something there i don't
know what section we're in of the
of the uh the solution raising right now
but that might be
we're about to flip over to sharing our
beautiful budget so if you want to do
that
go into that that is perfect okay cool
i'll put a pin on that
that's all for me daniel do you want to
go first and share your
sure um well
so my experience is it took me
so it took me a long time to figure out
which local church that uh
i joined that was aligned with my values
part of that was
um having lgbtq uh
acceptance um having women in leadership
um and i i found the episcopal church
um there are other churches and um
i guess the the point is that i have
found a lot of people don't know
that there are extremely liberal and
extremely
progressive uh communities um but
i still i mean i usually fall back on
using the word community i tell
some friends of mine you know i think
that
uh churches used to be like the
community hub um they were the center of
where people gathered um and
not just like once a week but like you
know they
they weren't a marketplace but they were
like a
um a social place and um
so you know i i even i tell some
folks that i run into and and some of my
friends
just come for the people just come for
the for the community you don't have to
believe a particular you know like
woo-woo
uh strange thing that is hard to believe
um
i wish i wish that uh
i guess my beautiful vision is that
people would um
find a way to gather and have
a multiplicity of of
beliefs and realize that the core of it
is is continuing
to work on how to treat one another
and love one another better and and
jared uh
mentioned something about um you know
what's the
what's the motivator and so there are
um religious communities that are doing
a lot of
charity work the the community i'm a
part of
um i mean i wish it was more they they
feed
we feed about 25 families a week that
are
that are very low income and we've got a
food pantry and it's like
okay this is good i have a very hard
time
we have so many people in my city but
they've got it's like there's this
blockage we're like oh it's a religious
thing
i can't i can't participate in that and
i feel like i have the freedom to go
wherever i can enter in a
a government type of community i can
enter in a secular community
i i can enter these spaces
and then when i look at folks that are
they're focusing on the bad parts of
religiousness they don't have the
freedom to enter
into those space and be like we're
trying to do good stuff we
you know we'd love more people to see
this as a community center
the only other community centers like
the mall but
um
i yeah i i i guess the beautiful vision
is is something like that
people could be way more open-minded and
and see
these spaces as more like community
spaces
um and drop the beliefs
that would be cool yeah it goes back to
what jared was saying before doesn't it
about
decoupling the dogma from the practice
you know i mean that seems to be
an absolutely essential feature of the
religion that isn't a religion of the
future right where everybody can buy
into it because there is no dogma that
you have to accept right
all you're actually buying into is good
faith participation
in regular practice i mean i think your
point about regularity danny was a
really important one right
and i didn't know that was the root of
the word but it's interesting that it is
and it's it
it that that commitment to do something
on a regular basis
is an essential part but it's but on its
own it's not enough right there is there
needs to also be
an earnestness and an authenticity of
engagement with it right that just
turning up is not enough
you have to turn up you know you have to
you have to bring
yourself as well right you you you've
got to turn up with all of yourself and
you know daniel was talking about i saw
daniel on the stowa recently he was
talking about this that
the dow that can be spoken is not the
dao right the dogma the rules the the
models can never be reality reality is
always beyond that right there is always
the unknown unknown which could cause
you to have to completely reframe
everything right so you can never be
100 certain of everything yeah you can
have high confidence in certain models
but there's always that
you know willingness to let them go and
and and so
what you have to do is not attach
sacredness to your models right that the
sacredness is reserved for the mystery
the mystery
is sacred right the the my
what i hold sacred i have to be willing
to let go of in the face of you know
what i mean
in the face of something new coming
along so that
the the cultivation of virtue
whatever that means right and if by
being virtuous that is putting yourself
in service to god or to the quran or
whatever then then fair enough right
there's nothing stopping you doing that
but the cultivation of virtue so that
you know when
your set of rules is always going to be
a circumstance we've got a gray area
it's on the bandwidth hang on actually
in this particular circumstance that
rule is wrong i disagree with the
application that
rule in that particular so how do you
become the kind of person that knows
that that
in this particular moment the rules by
which i normally abide
are not applicable how do you become
that person that's
that's the religion that isn't a
religion right is is having that
yeah i think i would build on that and
um
[Music]
i i it to me as you were speaking about
that
the the concern of
like how do you get people on the
um on the
the path of self-development to a point
where they can think for themselves and
don't need a book to tell them
what is right or wrong right like what
what
drives people on this path
and do people even need to
be on that path to get them
in the door of a community center right
and then that
to me the the big thing
that i look at what motivates society
right now
and i look at can we retrofit
whatever that is into bringing people
into community
and it looks like
some system of money or some system of
safety or some system of
providing goods and services
for an action is a motivating so
what if we what if you could retire off
of going to
a community center every week right like
what
what if by
participating in community you
afford yourself uh safety and security
your basic needs are covered
right like that well there's some kind
of system there that
if with modern technology we can
track and understand
like even just with the phones being
close enough to each other in a
proximity
like that can be motivation enough to
get people in the room
and then what happens in the room can be
anything you know you can you can format
that to be
um just community service helping people
whatever whatever the
factor is there but i i just i think
it's so important that there
is a some type of
positive motivator versus a punitive
motivator of
um current religions which is if you
don't do this
you're going to hell forever and like
that's just the constant fear in the
back of your head of like oh i need to
do
like it's like whipping the horse
instead of giving it a carrot
right and like i just feel as if the
the carrot versus the stick the carrot
is the better
strategy in creating a quote-unquote
religion it's not a religion
so so my my beautiful future
is both like for me myself i want access
to nature i want access to community
where we are looking out
after each other's needs it is
intergenerational
it is the religion that's not a religion
and you don't need to follow a dogma
i also see how religion
islam christianity judaism is very
important to people that i love
and i want them to have access to the
community and the religious
textbook that speaks to them i don't
really know how to square that circle in
that
it's hard to be part of a religion that
you think is saving someone's soul
and not spread it right not be like it's
the answer everyone
like if you're gonna go to hell if you
don't believe this i better tell you
about it
and at the same time finding that
ability to be like i will
help you find access to your religion
and and the more access you have the
more
um and mosques that they're available to
you the more
churches that are available to you the
more you're going to be able to find the
one that's in alignment you're still
going to be able to evolve and grow
in that faith and in that in in your
interpersonal life
and if you outgrow one you can find a
new one
right and and that there is a bigger
meta
community that has to support that um
and so that's my vision of a future is
that we do have the these tools to be
able to find that easily
and the tools to be able to create
communities that have no dogma
that are are next to like because i mean
all of them are going to have dogma
but it's figuring out where your dogma
is right and figuring out well how
do we need to believe in this right do
we need to to have this as our tenant
and the more you can do that with people
who are consciously
playing with that the more pointing out
dogma
becomes a benefit instead of a problem
right it's like oh i didn't even know i
was living by that tenant oh yeah no i
do assume everyone should live this way
like everyone should treat everyone with
kindness except or they shouldn't
like it's like right okay there is no
hard and fast rules so
that is a bit of my vision of the future
i i wonder i'm just sort of posing the
question here but the
it seems that the communities that
really stand the test of time and i'm
thinking of the amish and there's a it's
a german word
bruderhof something like that i'm not
sure i've got the word quite right but
it's something like that
um they are both strongly religious
communities right i mean they they they
believe strongly they adhere strongly to
the dogma i mean not just the prep the
practice and the dogma but the dogma
is is a is a rigid thing that holds them
all together and i wonder whether
long-standing communities can actually
exist without
some i mean not that dogma but some kind
of dogma that they all buy into
i mean i'm not saying it must be but it
certainly the evidence would suggest
that
it's an important thing however i don't
think
any of them very few of them can
actually draw people in
they um give birth to the people right
like you give you have a lot of babies
and most of them are going to stay
within that community because it's their
family in their community and some are
going to fall out
as long as your religion gives you more
than two babies
that's you know and that's a cultural i
mean i think about the churches i grew
up in
there were a ton of families who had 10
to 20 children
and because that's part of you know i
mean god gifting you life
and so that's a different enticement
than converting somebody right those are
completely different giving birth to
your clergy
versus creating something that is a
natural attractor
they somewhat have both but
like amish no one's no one's converting
to the amish lifestyle very few people
are converting to that choosing that it
has to be something they kind of were
born into
whereas there are people who choose
evangelical christianity and convert to
it
i would like to add it might be helpful
to make a difference
uh to notice a difference between um
the religious
a community and rituals
you could have a community of a hundred
people
and you may do a regular
ritual once every day at noon or
once every week um at noon
maybe 60 maybe 60 out of 100
participate in the ritual because that's
you know
what they like we would want to maybe
say that
the other 40 are still in the community
but they just don't do the ritual part
um and i'll tell you a story i i have a
friend that's very
into playing board games and getting
people together with
his board games you know very
straightforwardly atheist
guy awesome guy good friends with him
and
um well so like he fills his house and
he's like i can't really get many more
people in my house and i
i told him i was like man well i got
this great big building
um you know because at least in the
united states
with the history of these religious
centers i mean they do have a lot of
resources
pretty often they've got these buildings
and i've seen them converted into
other things one of them was bought and
turned into a coffee shop one was bought
and turned into a music studio
um i mean these are rare events but i
tell my friend i said
tell you what we can have a way bigger
euchre tournament
if you know he knows me really well i
don't
try to tell people what to believe but i
said we've got a great big basement over
here a bunch of tables a bunch of chairs
we could fit twice as many people as we
could in your house have a grand old
time
treat the basement of the of the
building
of the church building like an extension
of your house
and he can't do it and um and
it it breaks my heart because well you
know if there's a cross
on the wall or something i i just can't
do it and i
i strong i mean i'd love to find out
what people think what people think your
vampire this guy
can't bear to look across
and you tell them like man if you could
just get over
that i tell just ignore it this is an
extension of your basement and
we can get more people together than
trying to cram them this was pre-covered
um you know people in your house and
um that that's the
greater part of this that's the sad part
that i see of like what's going on
because
you know our society is like okay leave
this religion crap behind well we got
these great awesome
buildings
and but but so is it possible
for folks to even be part of a community
that is rooted
it's been held together by religious
people they still do their ritual on
sunday morning
and maybe you don't even show up on
but like the the building the community
i'm a part of there's stuff going on all
week
you could show up there basically any
time during the day
and you know well especially pre-covet
there's
there's a couple organizations there's
always something going on they're
filling
backpacks for low-income kids and
whatever you could just show up be like
what's going on here
you know um i don't know any other place
that is like that um and that's
you know part of why i picked this topic
to
talk about it and really try to
understand what do other people see when
they
when they what do other people think
when they see that kind of thing
so i think there's lots of possibility
in the next section
which is what can we do with ten
thousand people
and a hundred thousand dollars either
and
you know what i mean there's so many
directions to take it i'm sure we'll
take it all directions
of like how do you create the religion
that's not a religion how do you make
better use
of church space that is like amazing
real estate in fact a lot of it is um
what is the word community kitchens
they've been designated as community
kitchens which means you can
host banquets you can host these things
in a way that you can't just create a
kitchen and do it
schools and churches and there's a
there's that's a huge resource right to
be able to use those resources in a way
that
isn't under the umbrella necessarily of
the church i know
um the year after my mat leave where i
was the poorest i've ever been and i was
using food banks
and um there's one that was through a
church and they were the one that gave
you produce
but you had to wait for like two hours
before like you had to line up to get
the thing and they would pray beforehand
and it was in the church and there's
always like grossness associated with
that it's like you have to be
and this my parents my mom and her her
husband are part of the salvation army
and they do a lot of good work they're
also completely anti-lgbt even if they
say they're inclusive
and so it's like right how much good can
you do if you're doing that [ __ ] right
i'm not i'm not bringing my kid to your
church i'm not letting that be part of
the indoctrination
but how can you still do the good work
fully transparently right anyway there's
a lot of possibilities to take out i
will let
anyone anyone start who would like to to
start i i would just like to ask daniel
a question if i may about this buddy of
yours that
doesn't want to use the church hall what
exactly is
his objection well i mean what what
exactly is it rooted in do you know
he's very decidedly atheist um
it's good maybe no one's asking him to
pray or accept god right i mean
yeah i'm slightly befuddled as to why he
won't even enter the space that that
seems
quite extreme i'm curious as to exactly
what he is
afraid of what he thinks might happen if
he was to use this room right what
what what's the yeah because i
i i'm very clear to people that like you
know okay so i find this meaning in this
jesus
thing but i don't i i don't tell anybody
else they have to
be about that or you know some of the
other
you know weird metaphysical stuff about
eternity or whatever it's
the thing about me i can tell you more
about it
and he knows that i'll have to ask uh
more questions
um
did he come from a religious background
because that it could be deep
trauma from that like yeah and on the
flip side to the
solution raising so somebody like me
i wonder is it possible to have
a a community space
where this stuff is going on maybe you
have workshops
you have uh craft nights you have
um other art things happening you have
charity things happening
is it would it also be open for folks to
do
rituals once in a while if we're calling
like
the religious ceremony the spiritual
ceremony like a ritual
you know could i participate in that
community and then be like hey once a
month i'd like to
you know have an hour and do my ritual
like are we going to be inclusive all
the way around
or is it like well you got you keep your
ritual over there or whatever
this is this is a question i don't know
if it's way off topic yet but
for me transparency is a big part of
because i do have trauma having grown up
in a church that
is highly traumatic and at the same time
i don't hold enough stock in the church
to care about being in that physical
space right put a cross on it's the same
as the flying spaghetti monster to me
like it's like okay
this is it's it's fine if you find
solace there i want you to have it right
that is
um like what i said about that food bank
it's like that's
it's needs to be transparent okay this
is a church event we're gonna pray first
this is a euchre night there's no prayer
it's just a physical
entity right that doesn't mean there's
not going to be people there who do have
prayer as part of their thing hey
maybe you might pray before you have
your hand right
to see if god will help you out here but
that's not what this
is right this isn't and because i find
that a lot of churches salvation army
especially
like no no we're inclusive come be part
of it
and then it's like but but not if you're
gay but not if you're you know and
with that without the transparency it's
hard to be able to trust
is this a church event that you're just
trying to get me in the door
or is it an event happening in church
space
because those are very different and i
think if churches were more transparent
they were like yeah
we're not using it except on sunday
except for
all of these community events that we do
these ones are church related this is
boy and girl
boys and girls club nothing to do with
god this is a study group nothing
you know i mean this is a soup kitchen
yes we pray beforehand
you're welcome to pray to whatever god
you want right like to be more
more transparent to offer that right a
yelp can be something we do with ten
thousand like what is this church
let's give it five stars one star how
lgbt friendly is it
is there loud music is there quiet music
what is what is there that is
secular right if that's something that
you're i
went to a church this last few years
because i wanted that intergenerational
community i think it's called the united
church
they barely even use the word god but
like the sermons were boring and the
music wasn't fun i was like this
is no i don't enjoy being here
and so it's not meeting my need but
so close like so close to doing it but
not like
sorry
yeah there are more and more
denominations that are
moving towards lgbt acceptance women
equality and some of them are there and
you know
i took me a while to figure it out but i
found one
um and
but it is confusing
because many of them aren't there
and so um
it's
it's hard to know how to even work with
those people um
but just to understand that their
worldview is consistent within itself
but they can't
see things in a different way um
yeah to me it just seems
it seems like such an easy thing to do
to just retrofit all of the practices
that a church does
but take out religion in it and like
like for example like prayer right what
does prayer do
all right well prayer you're you're
thanking god in a lot of situations
you're you're being grateful
so it's like okay how do we retrofit
that all right let's go around in a
circle
and just say three things you're
grateful for and
let's say it out loud to other people
i'm thankful that i'm here i think that
and like that does the same thing it
like releases the serotonin
and like physiologically it does the
same thing right great
got that covered um reading from sermons
right bibles
make it a book club every month we have
a different book that's voted on by the
community
and the community reads the book and
talks about it and in small groups i
mean sure you can
do that that that's that's a fun kind of
communal communal event
um then like what what i mean
i feel like there are ways to
to take all of the things that
happen in a religion or in a
like like look at all the world
religions look at what
they do in common and then retrofit
those things give that as a meta
protocol
to um people who want to start their own
things and just like
just there's got to be something that
will arise from that i'm sure somebody's
working on that by now you'd think
to me it would be more coming from the
direction of the individual
like i said my my part of church is
singing with other people in nature well
i need nature to sing
and i need other people if i want other
people to join me and so being able to
say hey this is what i want
who else is this called to is very like
grant doing church and retrofitting it
is like telling the people who are there
your prayer isn't working right like
that's not their version of prayer their
version of prayers they're talking to
god
and yes they're grateful and yes they
can like pass
off hey i have cancer if it's in your
will please cure it
that's very different than like when you
don't believe there's a god right
there's no one to pray to
what are you gonna do with my cancer i
wish i could give it up and
like i wish i could go back to that
belief system and so i don't want to
take that belief system away from other
people
um but to be able to create from the
ground
up what do what are the pieces you need
to put together right what are your
rituals what are the things
and where it makes sense to have one
community and a physical location great
and we can retrofit churches in if
they're willing to right
hey they're pretty taken up during the
weekend but hey if we want a wednesday
morning service
this one is i don't remember it's one of
the canadian shows and it takes place in
a small town
and they have one church and it's like a
one-room little church and it turns into
the mosque on saturday and it's like the
i think friday night it's the it's like
there's like one jewish family it's like
okay
like there's something beautiful about
that if the space wants it
right like if it's something that
they're offering to people and it could
be something that is
done with 10 000 people right what fuels
your soul
and helping people find that helping
people find what it is
that their church from their childhood
gave them or what they thought church
would give them if they never had that
and how can we give that to each other
how can we offer that
10 000 people hundred thousand dollars
10 000 people
well i like what was said about
transparency um
that's helpful um that's helpful to
understand
uh even more and um
because yeah i'm very aware that there's
language that's very triggering
to some people so
um yeah can it can
churches can seem like they can do like
a bait-and-switch kind of thing
um i was just at a a big volleyball
event and uh it was not a church
function but a large church group showed
up and we're all playing volleyball
and uh they had a speaker and a
microphone
and some leader type of person that made
an announcement
kind of stopped all the volleyball
happening so that they could do a prayer
over the whole volleyball
thing and it was like you just really
mixed volleyball
with your specific um
with your specific religious thing and
you got a bunch of people here who were
just playing volleyball and like you
just did that to everybody
um which i don't think was very nice
um but
sorry so yeah
when you know in your heart that you're
right and that you're saved you want
everyone else
to have the same thing right and it's
it's yeah it's very hard to turn that
[ __ ] off it's it really is
and that is like when we're so like
christianity is part of our culture
very deeply part of our culture in north
america
even when it's not right we have
christmas we have easter
and so it becomes the blanket the
blanket thing
like i was part of a brain tumor group
and
it was like okay only science i was like
but every time someone had a surgery
they're like
right tell us your surgery so we can
pray for you i was like
what what like that's you're not even
asking if that's their religion do you
want me to pray for you do you want me
to have a positive thought on that day
like what's gonna
help you it's like just normal that it's
prayer and it's like people you know
essential oils cure and it's like no no
not unless it's scientific i'm like
then why are we allowing prayer and i
got kicked out of the group it's like
because of course we allow prayer that's
the thing that we do in society
oh like and i i really appreciate what
jared said about the retrofitting so
like
even in the situation that i saw last
week with the volleyball thing
it would be very different if
i mean i'd have to think it through a
little bit but it'd be very different if
someone
came up and said i just want to
encourage everybody
to have a fun time have a safe time and
just
love one another while you're playing
volleyball that
would feel encouraging and add some
energy and
they you know almost said ver something
very similar like that and then they
just say
in jesus name
on you just did that to everybody just
leave it at
you know so yeah just leave it at the
love one another while you're playing
volleyball or whatever positive
spin you wanted to put on the moment
great but then you just made it right
you made it dogmatic
um and we didn't enter into your
house of worship you came to like the
public volleyball thing
um so but with
you guys in america you particularly
lost the plot with with the religion
thing because you know you can't get
elected as president there unless you
profess
a belief in god right i mean it's just
not possible
even the most obviously non-religious
obama right had to profess a belief in
god otherwise he couldn't get elected
you know
it's it's you guys corinthians 2
corinthians 2 it's my favorite like
that's
not how you say that if you've ever went
to church ever
for one sunday it's like this one's my
favorite
second corinthians you mean second
corinthians right
if you had a 100 000 and you know
a group of dedicated people that were
maybe locally organized
you could yeah you could do some kind of
community center that was more inclusive
um let me ask you something do you think
whether you think this would fly so you
were talking before about rituals sorry
my neighbor came by i had to slip away
for a few minutes so i missed some of
the conversation but scrolling back to
before
i walked away you were talking about
rituals and i was wondering
in a sort of communal center of some
kind
could you have you know um different
types of religious ceremonies could you
run
a jewish and a christian and a muslim
i'm different not at the same time right
on different days whatever and those
that want to come to one country
but i mean would would a jew go to a
religious ceremony in a space where
muslims had been
german in the same space that had been
used by muslims or christians or hindus
or whatever
on previous occasions i'm thinking about
your friend who won't even walk in and
use it as a room you know put up some
tables and gather people there
you know would would that fly would you
have to come up with rituals which were
which would actually be an interesting
challenge to see if you could come up
with rituals which were meaningful
for all of these religions and didn't
step on any of their toes
it would be very interesting to see if
you could actually do that you know that
still acknowledge the existence of god
of the supreme power of our
you know of our unworthiness in the in
the face of this supreme power and blah
blah
blah blah blah but but not use language
which would trigger
any one particular is that possible do
you think
well i was going to mention my community
that i'm part of
has people of varying many different
religions
and they put on events and invite people
to them
right here's passover you're welcome to
come here's one of the guys does a
a chanting and chocolate every every
month
and he's jewish and it's in hebrew right
like it's it's beautiful poetry in
hebrew but you don't need to be jewish
to participate
and that same that you're invited you're
invited to come be part of this ritual
even though you're clearly not going to
know what passover is and we'll have to
explain it to you and you know like
there's a very big difference also when
you invite people in who aren't part of
it
versus this is like of course you pray
before a volleyball tournament everyone
prays before a volleyball tournament
right
like there's that very big difference of
its secular
and again that transparency right of
like the community i'm part of isn't one
community it isn't a christian community
it isn't a jewish community
and so therefore everyone's invited if
it was a christian community it probably
wouldn't be as comfortable having
passover
or ramadan there doesn't happen to be
anyone who's
muslim who lives there but yeah i don't
know
how you could design one ritual that
would
be fulfilling for these different faiths
um but could one building have
a ritual for different faiths on
different nights that would probably
just depend on how
fundamentalist the individuals were
you know as the jordan peterson thing on
open-mindedness
plays a factor right like for me myself
yeah no problem super open-minded
i can i can see things in
you know 50 different ways and and
adjust but i definitely understand that
there's folks that
don't their personality doesn't do that
and so
that might be more of what we're talking
about anyways
i i think i think that the situation
that we are in right now which is
one of um
the older generation having
the community and belief systems that
they have
and then not having
anything for the next generation
to move into that's not that
right like like to me that seems like an
issue like
it to be able to take the fundamentals
of
um what brings together good community
separated entirely from religion
and just provide that for people
in in one way or another incentivize it
i mean the the imagery that keeps coming
to my head is that like
it's like it's like there are a bunch of
horses down in a pasture and they're
grazing and the grass is dead
and like old but that's they think that
that's the only grass that's there
so you just get a carrot and you slowly
lead the horse
to another stable that's filled with
tons of amazing hay and it's just so
good
and as soon as they step in that hay and
they start eating it they're like wow i
can't believe
that that was what i was eating the
whole time right like
that to me seems like a metaphor
for what kind of needs to happen
or would be great to happen in the
future is provide a
an alternative that's just so clearly
better than what has been done
in terms of community only like getting
people
to to to commune together
without the extra added dogma that they
have to
cognitively you know they run into
cognitive dissonance trying to
to rationalize in today's world like
and then slowly incentivize people to
participate in those communities
and how how's that gonna happen time
banking or
um whatever i mean there's so many
different ways that it could happen
but um that that to me seems like it's
it's the the path is not trying to
convert the people that are already
deeply in set set in their ways
but for the next generations to provide
something that is
equal to if not better than the
community
that's provided through church um
so that they can have something that
they can look to
yeah i i would add that you know your
idea earlier
about your gratitude
yeah what you said hey on
on friday we're going to do one hour
gratitude meditation uh
or a gratitude ceremony and you're
you're welcome to come and you know you
design it without
any of the religious dogma
specific faiths or something like that
um and like would that be valuable to
people
um the and just again what i notice
is it's it's a real estate thing it's
like
i can't it's very hard how do i do that
i've nowhere to go and i when i walk
around my city
it's like those buildings with these
great multi-purpose rooms and
the space are all the churches um
i can't what am i supposed to do make a
partnership with the coffee shop and be
like hey on friday nights i want to like
empty out your space and we're gonna do
a gratitude meditation i mean maybe i
could convince someone but
i think that's something we could
absolutely do with ten thousand people
and a hundred thousand dollars is have a
database of churches that have space
available whether they're renting it out
or gifting it out
to say hey here's who we're willing to
gift it out to here's who we're not
willing to gift it out to
and here's what the rental is if you're
not for profit versus for whatever it
happens to be
able to just coordinate that real estate
right they do
have really expensive real estate
because they've been in the business for
so long
the united church that i went to i mean
they have a beautiful
corner lot on in vancouver and they're
talking about like
are they gonna sell it and buy a new one
or what are they gonna we're gonna do
with that land
but um to be able to to use that real
estate
is one option to be able to have a yelp
for
for religious type community of hey is
this
what religion is it are they lgbt
friendly not do they say they're lgbt
friendly people who have been there in
our lgbt
did you feel welcome or did you feel
like they were just trying to get you
not to have sex
with the same like there's a very big
difference of like you're welcome here
but not your sin
when you're not you know those are very
different things
that having um there's
a online church service that i attend
sometimes on sunday by a woman called
unicol
she has this thing called unicult and it
is just an online you're like
it's it's very tongue-in-cheek about
about being in a cult and i really like
it and um
having something like that that is hey
where do you come because one of the
questions
all of this secular type religion stuff
united church all of it are you tithing
of your income because that's how the
church runs like that is how they
provide having a clergy how they can do
the work in the community
and so any of the stuff we've created
we're getting near the end of the hour i
would like to invite us each to go
around and say what the most powerful
thing is that you would like to see what
i would like that to be
is what would you put ten dollars in not
ten percent of your income
what would you put ten dollars into so
that you had access to it
have a um not necessarily
the like it to take that a step further
in terms of
um you know churches renting out space
and having space for things like
to literally find the churches that have
sold them
like they've sold somewhere or they are
looking to sell
to completely revamp so that you can
take down all of the
religious uh icons and
make it so that it's truly non-religious
as a space that can then be retrofitted
to have community there for not like
within another system because
the same issue with your friend who's
atheist he won't even step foot in a
building that has a church a cross on it
and i think there's a lot of people that
are like that that are so traumatized by
religion
that they just can't have that anymore
and like i think
that to have for ten thousand people and
a hundred thousand dollars
like i would put ten dollars into
a um an initiative
that is looking to convert
the places that didn't make it
into something else that is
separated from religion but can be
providing the same types of things into
society
i can go um i usually think very locally
so like i think very little i'm getting
echo
so um
i would i would put 10 into
kind of program where i could ran
a multi-purpose with your level
does that go really bad
all right i keep meeting you and you're
on meeting and reviewing and unbeating
yeah okay we're good sorry go daniel
let's try this again okay uh some some
kind of thing where i could
put ten dollars into renting uh
space in one of these
one of these church buildings you know
with other people maybe there's a way
that i
you know send an application and say
like here's what i want to do
and you know let them be
you know more hands off and say yeah i
want to do this meditation
i need a space to do it can i rent one
of your rooms
um it would have to be really
inexpensive i think um but
that'd be cool
about you eric is there anything that
you think would be powerful well i don't
i don't really have anything i just find
it very interesting that in a discussion
about religion we haven't really talked
about religion in the sense that most
people would understand the word at all
right whether
it's all community centers and you know
repurposing buildings and
absolutely nothing to do with uh you
know with god or
death or which which is which is good
which is i think
it's fine it seems to be sort of a tacit
acknowledgement that actually what
religion is about is people getting
together and doing [ __ ] together right
and
and and forming relationships in the
process of doing [ __ ] together
is is is the heart of what religion is
actually about so yeah
i i find that quite encouraging that
that seems to just be the except
you know without any question that's
what seems to be the accepted
framework a little bit how we framed it
we were talking about religion at the
community we have completely just
accepted that frame right god's barely
come up
well we could probably all talk for
hours about the negative
parts that we've all either seen or
observed or heard about
um and like it's part of what i said at
the beginning
do a whole other solution raising on
that one because yeah i think there is
too much power that the clergy have in
every single church and it's why they're
able to abuse power
to children to to vulnerable people in
their community
that they have the answers and whether
it's a cult cult something that started
and you're like how does anyone believe
that
or something that's been around for
thousands of years when somebody has
the key to your soul that is a power
dynamic that can be easily abused and we
need more transparency and more
ability and so for me the thing i would
put ten dollars towards is to be able to
give
myself and other people the resources of
knowing what events are happening that
is going to fuel my soul right nissan
unit nature
as well as to be able to have that that
share in the real estate of church that
they're putting forward
i don't know how feasible it is to buy
those things because they are
extremely expensive like the united
church if they're selling theirs to
people they're going to sell it at pr
at the same value as everything else
they just happen to have a bundle of
land
they're not going to sell it at a cheap
rate because you're doing good good
god's work right unless
it's to their own religion and but
finding a way that you can
share in that and start that community
so it's like okay maybe we're just using
it on tuesdays and yes knowing there's a
big cross on the wall if that's a
problem for you this is not the place
for you to be but this one has a star of
david does that make you feel more
comfortable like this one has
what's the what's the symbol that's
going to be the least offensive to you
but it's more about hey we need a place
to have a a we need a place to host this
book club
is it no is the church okay with us
hosting it here what are the
implications and to be able to ourselves
um
maybe this is way too much to do for a
hundred thousand dollars but a yelp for
churches to be able and to be able to
share in
this space and find your own community
it's in alignment with
what you what you do jared did you have
a chance to share during this part i
don't remember
is there how's my echo am i right
i think you're good as long as daniel's
not talking all right
yeah no uh the
i guess i'm i'm i think it's
i think it's gonna have to be
i think with ten thousand people and a
hundred thousand
dollars just the
if we found ten thousand people
that were willing to
rethink what this could be
i would put like i'd put ten dollars to
join that group
right like if it was like a online
community that has brainstorming
sessions
or that is making like literally making
a book maybe like
make having an instruction manual for
the average person to follow
that doesn't have religion in it but has
like everything else that goes in there
like just
take out the dogma and like
here's how to run a a like here's an
instruction manual that you can use
to run a community in a repurposed
church
right like that that would be really
powerful for me um
and then people can go and like when
some of these churches that have
lost membership and need to sell at a
really low price
like then you can get pool funds and
have
people buy those if there's enough
people in that area
and then all they have to do is work on
this community wiki
take this community wiki and run their
community via these meta plans
that are being developed by this larger
group
right so um that's just an idea that i
was thinking about but
i i just i i'm very averse to
the idea of
trying to like i just i really think
separating religion completely
from the community is
something that's going to be necessary
in the long run because
no matter what there's always going to
be
if you're i don't know right
yeah you mean separating the dogma from
the from the community aspect is that
yeah yeah there's there's just so many
there's so many traps in religion
and in the way it's designed and why
it's such a good
hook and why it has such good staying
power
that why it's been around for so many
millennia like
there just needs to be instead of
trying to work with and retrofit
just something else that people can can
go to that doesn't
that doesn't have that that doesn't
matter there's something better
like something that that is do you not
think the fear of death
is a big part of this you know i think
it was jubilee mentioned this i think it
was jubilee mentioned this earlier on in
the conversation
manipulating our fear of death right we
know don't worry we know what's going to
happen after you die and if you do these
things you're going to go to a good
place but if you don't do these things
you're going to go to a bad place right
and that
it seems to me that until we at an
individual level overcome our fear of
death and just accept it as the
inevitability that it is right
and and and live our lives guided by
the fact that we're going to die right
that our mortality is actually the thing
that gives our life meaning and brings
it into focus right i mean
until we as individuals get to that sort
of
place
the fear of death
i think you'll know that sorry i just
muted you jared before he started
talking
although we're at the hour so if you
just want to give your uh closing
thought
jared and then i will stop the recording
sure i was gonna say just real quick um
just it could literally be designed as a
like post-religious
like antidote right like it could be
designed saying okay
if you come from this religion here's
some resources if you come from this
religion here's some resources
like boom boom like here's some things
that have helped the other people
kind of transcend and include
whatever all of that was like
you can all talk about it together in
this community right but it's not it's
it's separate from this whole thing it's
this whole thing when you have
questions about death and about all
these things like
this guy is is thinking about um
simulation theory and
why we're all in a simulation maybe talk
to him or maybe this or maybe that or
like there are so many other like what
have people
gravitated towards that give them solace
about death that isn't religion
and bring those together in one place
and and allow for a migration
that is that that migrated for the next
generation it's right
it's it's not trying to convert people
already there but
to prevent more people from being just
stuck
in one place with no other options
that's kind of my
like i feel like there needs to be
something
all right thank you yeah my closing
while you were talking was
to have a meta like all those big
questions that religion solves where do
we go after death what is the purpose of
life
what are we even to be able to not
answer those for people but give them
places to go to have to talk to other
people about them would be really cool
all right stop him recording